[
    {
        "question": "The ...... is the nominal head of the state.",
        "options": [
            "Chief Minister",
            "Governor",
            "Chairman",
            "President"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Distinguished personalities from various fields are nominated by ...... to the Vidhan Parishad.",
        "options": [
            "Chief Minister",
            "Speaker",
            "Governor",
            "Chairman"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "...... is appointed by the president.",
        "options": [
            "Mayor",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Governor"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "Maharashtra is divided into territorial constituencies for the purpose of ......",
        "options": [
            "Voting",
            "Elections",
            "Education",
            "Business"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "The proceedings of the Vidhan Sabha are carried out under the supervision and guidance of the ......",
        "options": [
            "Chairman",
            "Speaker",
            "Mayor",
            "Chief Minister"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Maharashtra has a ...... legislature",
        "options": [
            "Bicameral",
            "Unicameral"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "...... is the first house of the Maharashtra legislature and comprises of 288 members.",
        "options": [
            "Vidhan Parishad",
            "Vidhan Sabha"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "Maharashtraâ€™s legislature conducts minimum ...... sessions in a year.",
        "options": [
            "Two",
            "Three",
            "Four",
            "One"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chief Minister ...... in issues facing the state and comfort the people.",
        "options": [
            "Creates",
            "Intervenes",
            "Develop",
            "Co-ordinate"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Any citizen residing in Maharashtra and who has completed ...... years of age can contest the elections to the Vidhan Sabha.",
        "options": [
            "25",
            "30",
            "18",
            "21"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "There are ...... members in the Vidhan Parishad of Maharashtra",
        "options": [
            "70",
            "78",
            "65",
            "60"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "India has adopted ...... system of government.",
        "options": [
            "Monarchy",
            "Dictatorship",
            "Unitary",
            "Federal"
        ],
        "answer": 4
    },
    {
        "question": "It was decided to form the status on the basis of ......",
        "options": [
            "Culture",
            "Area",
            "Language",
            "Diversity"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The leader of the majority party in Legislative Assembly becomes the ......",
        "options": [
            "Governor",
            "Chief Minister"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "The nature of government machinery in all ...... of India is same.",
        "options": [
            "States",
            "Area",
            "Ward"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chief Minister bears the ultimate responsibility of the efficient ......",
        "options": [
            "Government",
            "Federal",
            "Administration",
            "Working"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The Chief Minister along with his ...... are collectively responsible to the Legislature Assembly.",
        "options": [
            "Council of Ministers",
            "MLA",
            "Speaker",
            "Portfolios"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "When the legislature is not in session and needs arises to make laws governor can issue ......",
        "options": [
            "A Bill",
            "A Proposal",
            "an Ordinance",
            "An Order"
        ],
        "answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "The governor has the right to ...... the session of the State Legislature.",
        "options": [
            "Summon",
            "Call",
            "Conduct",
            "programme"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "India has a large geographic expanse with a ...... population.",
        "options": [
            "Language",
            "Multicultural",
            "Large",
            "Crowded"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Maharashtra is one of the ...... states in India.",
        "options": [
            "Progressive",
            "Developed",
            "Advance",
            "Modernized"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "India has ...... constituent states",
        "options": [
            "28",
            "29"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "In the ...... system, the government exists in the two levels.",
        "options": [
            "Federal",
            "Central",
            "State"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "The members of state legislatures are known as ......",
        "options": [
            "Members of legislature Assembly",
            "Members of Executive Assembly"
        ],
        "answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "Only ...... states in India have two houses.",
        "options": [
            "Seven",
            "Eight",
            "Five",
            "Ten"
        ],
        "answer": 1
    }
]